Council meeting for August 23rd, 2021.
We're out of work, so.
We're going to do the pledge of leads on.
We're going to do the pledge of leads in six and a pair of six.
Yeah, okay.
Okay.
That's all right.
That's one.
All right.
We're going to do a proclamation.
First off, for Mr. Curt Moore.
And Curt is right here in front of us.
What are you?
I'm going to do three.
Four.
And Curt.
I'm going to talk to his mom and start a lemonade stand out
for other house.
And he raised $2,500.
About $2,045.
Wow.
And the reason he wanted to put that on is to help
by the kids in the community of schools,
supplies.
And I thought it was worthy of a proclamation in Curt's honor.
And so Curt, we're going to.
I'm going to have to hand you this proclamation.
That proclamation is almost as big as he is.
You know sometimes even the youngest our community can set an example for the rest of us.
And, you know, Curt, Curt stepped out and thought of others before himself.
And I noticed that lots of people aren't community stopped by our firefighters or police officers.
And a lot of people stopped by.
So Curt, we thank you.
And next time you have one, Holler, we'll try to get the city council there.
Not all at one time.
We don't have the poster.
Three public input or on schedule personal conferences.
We have an forward discussion of the good neighbor coalition.
Mr. Rick Aldrich.
And I do not see Rick on a few thousand six.
All right.
We'll skip that one for now.
If Rick comes in, we will.
You'll back to him.
So five consent agenda.
And I think suggest we.
You'll prove I'm sixty seven.
That correct.
Just sixty eight sixty seven.
So that proves I'm sixty eight.
We'll move.
Hold on a second.
Davis.
Aye.
Parker.
Thunder.
Keystep.
Aye.
And then nine's on the table.
Nine will come back to you later.
No, no, answer it.
That's the one we're working for.
Okay, we're going to table number nine.
Ten.
Approve.
Removal.
A mayor's systems advisory cooperative advisory board member, Lacey Perry.
From office.
You need a motion.
So moved.
Second.
Okay.
Davis.
All right.
Double.
Cumber.
Parker.
I can't move on.
Keystep.
All right.
11.
Approve.
Economic development contract.
With minor area.
Economic development services.
And the minor area chamber commerce.
Shout out.
How.
We've been up to this.
We've killed them.
We just asked.
We're going to ask the one small change in it.
On.
Okay.
There's a section that we haven't been utilizing.
And no, I'm discussing it.
That says states as a client will not be charged for use of names or chamber advertising opportunities.
And the client's logo will be used in all the service providers for parking and advertising.
We'll see those in the electronic format and just format.
We just wanted to change the word.
We'll be used to can be used.
Because there may be some things.
Something that maybe the city.
Doesn't want their logo on it.
We're doing, you know, some legislative stuff to the chamber and things like that.
And we thought it might give us a little more flexibility.
So it would just be that one word that we would propose.
Changing.
In a contract.
Great.
What does the contract expire?
Um.
You know.
It's for a year.
So it just got renewed.
Yeah.
Well, we're.
We're.
It's late.
Yeah.
We don't pay the quarterly.
So it really is just now coming up.
I go.
And it.
The client's logo can be used instead of willing.
It's.
That would go when I have some flexibility.
And maybe there's some things.
The city.
Doesn't necessarily want their logo on.
Yeah.
It's just putting it on everything.
So we're proving that the contract.
Extention or just the word change.
But.
Both.
Both provided that this word can change.
Correct.
Understood.
Thank you.
Right.
So you can kind of update for us at all.
Well, you said they were in heading for communication solutions.
Of course, you all know that.
They're back to a hundred and thirty employees.
They have more women there than I actually thought they did.
They're willing to expand at least some other 250.
We're negotiating with the Department of Humor for now.
We're going to continue to project for them to expand here in my amount of
momentum.
So that would be in additional ten or fifty jobs on top of the hundred and the
thirty they've already added.
And we're working with several of our manufacturers.
I didn't tell you right now where about seventy percent through our business
retention and expansion.
What's mean we do out with the committee and has manufacturers and
primary employers are all the same questions.
We'll turn around and do it again for commercial services and retail
in gaining weight.
And of course, I can tell you what we're talking about.
And that workforce is a major issue.
That about fifty percent of our manufacturers would expand right now.
So we're working with them to do everything we can to get people here.
We've been in touch with the city for some things like that.
Since the last time I presented, I will tell you with our working on some of the
VBA funding that has come out.
And of course, we'll partner closely with the city, the tribes,
Kyler and I have been talking and we'll continue to.
And we have been getting some questions from many actors.
We're learning the the ice storm and February.
And we've made sure to put Tyler in contact with them or work closely with him as well.
And so we're going to reach out to Green Day Way and see if there's something
we can do is apply once you create a couple of them.
Otherwise it's just kind of the same thing.
We're doing really well.
We're on a tight road.
I have been saying for the last few months.
As long as we continue to head my direction, I think we've got a lot of
great coming to my end.
I will say the COVID numbers have started to slightly affect
the manufacturers because if someone's vaccinated and they get exposed,
it's usually that whole group that has to be quarantined.
And so like one of my manufacturers for instance,
sold half in our products.
He did last year and made the same revenue because his product has gone up so high.
But he could have sold double.
He didn't have the employees.
So that's our big concentration right now.
It's figuring out a way to get more employees in the region.
But everyone in the country is working.
Sure that I won't speak for rest of the council that I sure will speak for myself.
I have asked on more than one occasion and would really appreciate
that I'd be added to distribution lists.
So when ribbon cuttings and any other thing that we can attend
happen, I get it.
We want the citizens and the businesses and whoever else to know
that.
We value their input and their activity in our community and if I can get there, I'm coming
But I've not been notified yet.
I would get with Cindy and rectify that immediately.
I know she's had some challenges with the database, but I'm surprised she doesn't have even.
So I'll get her to see.
I actually asked Cindy a couple of times and gave her everyone or email addresses to add to the list
because I would like for all of us to get that case I can't be there.
Rod maybe it will be there.
So someone from the council can be there to show that business partner that we care and we
want to be there.
That's the support.
Okay.
I'll get it to you here.
Thank you.
So you can verify that all the council members are included and I just should be.
We'll put that over put you guys in the database but I'll keep you on my list as well.
So whenever I get them I can just board them and just make sure.
Thank you.
It's easier if I just send yoke calendar to my cousin and roll on to that.
I don't care how it gets or someone's.
Any questions for Charlotte?
I have those that may not have been on her last time.
Can we go over some of the details of the contract, provide them out and what's paid and all that?
I can do that.
Sure.
And so the city enters into the contract with May's economic development authority here in the city.
And my, my area is a pretty standard between cities and economic development authorities.
It's a $50,000 contract to the economic development.
So it's a substantial part of our budget.
The contract goes through the services rendered.
But it's to which are community affairs activities and economic development.
There is some stuff in there about confidentiality on both sides because it's a section of
the world peace for the city and for us when we're working at economic development projects.
It also includes $16,000 credit towards utilities for the building that we're in.
So we share with the chamber as well as several entrepreneurs.
Can we have our membership to go ahead?
That's kind of the gist of it.
It's renewed or not renewed every year.
And we present them a quarter of the basis to let you know what's going on.
It's paid out clearly as well.
If anything did happen in the city felt like that they didn't want to continue the contract.
You have that opportunity throughout the year.
And you're not the hands strength.
Hands strength to it.
The entire area.
So I will come to report to you all.
You can ask questions.
And also that you're more than welcome to come meet with me at any time as well.
We can go over.
economic development, a lot of times just kind of going over the basics of what we do with our
revolving ones and everything else makes it a little easier to understand yet.
And I think this was started after the revolving ones and was transferred over two days.
I think that's one of the sort of, that one I started, that one I started doing it, that was my understanding.
Is there any other communities that you're represented in other than Miami or working for the Miami?
We do work recently throughout the county sometimes.
The reason for that being, there isn't, a lot of these small towns on how to train the economic development.
And so they will reach out to me and we'll work with them at a few that have industrial parks.
And so, you know, maybe helping them identify what this is or infrastructure that they need, connecting them with Grand Big Way or Council of Governments.
We do some things like that.
We do work with any factors in the whole county.
Is there any other town or city that is also funding you guys other than the city of Miami?
Not at this time. There are a few that are chamber members and they will fund the chamber.
So are you not pressuring them to help fund, to where Miami is not the only one funding you money?
We do.
We have started letting them know that for my services, this is what has to happen.
If you remember the town we're talking about, our commerce, all-minded, and it's not going to be easy to understand the world for them to make it a priority for economic development.
So is Miami your priority?
My husband has always been like, but regionalism has to be part of the economic development.
And I will always say that I'm not going to lie to you about that.
If I can't present regionally, this I can solve this focus and continue because there are workforce, doesn't come from just my name on.
So I have to know what's available throughout the region.
And any economic development that are available.
So how else do you guys raise funds?
We, so the city is about to program about it.
And that we also raised funds to our revolving one fund and through financial partners, several of the banks do a financial commitment.
And there's also private manufacturers that will do a commitment because we help them.
Sure, did you have any data that, like, tangible data that would support what impact this group has had on the growth of Miami as far as we've given you this amount of money?
How much is that like the new call center that's coming for example?
Yeah, so we run an important analysis based on them bringing 150 jobs to Miami at the moment, which started at 730.
So we're 1.3 million within the first year.
Thank you.
And that's indirect.
That's not even direct, just the salaries, that's indirect as far as like sales tax.
And then shopping at the global places and meeting at the global income.
No, no, the $12.
for a quarter, their specific things that can be spent on that.
We added that to the contract this year.
We, and at what we're thinking, and what we talked about is at the end of the year, we
will show you what we spend on, of course we can do that at any time.
But it's, those funds are going to be used for memberships and subscriptions.
So, for example, I'm the representative for the area on the select of Oklahoma Committee,
which is the economic development organization in the state.
Also, with Northeast Oklahoma Regional Alliance, with Grand Caveway, and several other entities
of the case-deadness of our constituents.
Those, also, those do-ness of preference, also pay for, like, if I, well, they pay, so that I can go to the
conference.
We pay for the conference.
But I'm not subscribed to those words, I can't go to the state.
And so those do-ness of preference allow me to pay other funds to be able to go memberships and
the state and my, and I'm only going to call trips and get us back to the state.
It also pays for maintenance for the building and insurance for the building and the
spec building of our funds that we're going to use in court as well.
And let's see, accounting for our audits, advertising for the website, site consult, publications,
lecturances, we're listing the spec building and several site consults and magazines.
Do-ness and subscriptions, insurance, including the speculation building and my MMA and our
pairs and maintenance of my MMA.
Those are the things that we earmarked for the city's money, so that you all will know
what you're doing.
We're looking okay.
Yeah, questions for Charlotte, so we're looking for a motion.
I'll make a motion that we approve the contract.
So if they can't get me out with the change.
With the change.
Second.
Mr. Speaker.
512, the Oklahoma Senior Games presentation.
Mr. Janet Robinson.
They're mинsighs to me in here today and needed so much activity and my name's Janet
Baltimore.
And I'm mayor in the bottom of the net, it's a golf court for my nose help.
A few years ago we received a card available to contact the senior patients and so since
hit late guys since he was the age 12, we decided to try that.
It was a whole different year for our last time as we played, we played, we played, we played.
We also did white lift and we found out that all states have seen their names.
So for the next 12, 13 years, we tried to low the United States and he played in the
secret pins.
And so he's one about 50 medals, which is pretty interesting.
So about three years ago, Kathleen Fitzgerald called me and she asked him, I would work with
tribal nations.
And to work with tribal nations, we would hear a few weeks ago, and we made a presentation
to him, and then that time was over there.
So I got to call him up and go on this to come here today.
And so I'm thrilled to be here today, the mission of our senior hands is to come up, help
and wellness for people 50 and over through education, fitness, and sports.
I'll come up with a 25 plus different events, and I have left all that up here for you on
the United States, and the ones that qualify in each state, in each of these sports, in each
state has one of the sports they work, the top athletes in each age group are invited in the
national team of your hands.
The national team of games is a world largest for you that people over 50, every year they have
a national team of your games, and at this, they have the body with the torch, they have the
Olympic village, and all the wonderful things that know a little bit, and this year we
will be having all of our, I say that, but it's national, it's a beautiful form.
And the package that I've put up here before you, you'll have our registration book that gives you
a lot more about whooply are and what we do.
You'll have a better with age, but up there, which is a story about my husband and I last year, it's
the way we familiar our games in the open city area.
There's also a lot of spinach magazine showing how we promote our games.
Also, you have packets that they're on how to start your own games.
Our CEO, Kathleen, has a couple of videos she'd like to show you, and then we'll be able to
answer in question, thank you, my dad.
Computer, whoo, this is, this is a video from national senior games.
So this is what seniors 50 and over are capable of doing.
She's 103.
Now she's 105.
They have sprints.
They have distance, pole pole thing, hammer grow.
Along young.
Swimming.
Pickleball.
Softball.
Sightling.
And they also bring the culture of the region.
Who is one of the founders?
Are you kidding me?
Are you sure?
Race walking.
At video was from Nationals.
Now you get to see our Oklahoma Senior Games video.
We're at the bottom with when it comes to heart disease and diabetes.
We're at the top.
I mean, you know what I'm saying.
We're at the back.
We're seeing your games.
Our athletes are in the middle.
Right in the middle of the states.
These are all the different events that we offer here in Oklahoma,
Escapald teams.
The reason that we're here is we represent the state games.
A lot of seniors, however, it's not easy for them to travel
more than 30 minutes, 45 minutes away from home,
but they also want to participate and want to be part of the games.
And by having local games throughout the state,
what that does is that enables more people to participate.
And also because people participate locally,
they are more aware of the state games,
which in turn makes people more aware of national games.
So what we're here to do is to introduce you to the state games
and hope that you will then your parks and recreation department.
We'll want to work with the tribes, with visitors,
bureau, to host senior games here in Miami.
So does anybody have questions that they would like to have?
And you totally control your games.
Nobody's telling you which games to have, or which games not to have.
Eventually, what we'll do is the local games will be qualifying sites
for state games that doesn't happen here currently,
but eventually we hope to do that.
And the other communities that host local games,
you can host local games, Oklahoma City,
art more, more Norman,
I think I forgot.
Oh, Muscogee, I almost forgot Muscogee.
So those are our local games and still a lot of...
water was prepared to, but the virus shut them down.
So does anybody have questions?
Sir, your local ones again?
Norman Moore, Oklahoma City, Yukon.
Art Moore, Muscogee, did I forget anything about it?
I think that's it, and still water would have.
They were on tap to have them.
And the local games are usually held in the spring.
And then our state games are held in the September and October.
So eventually they'll qualify in the spring and into the summer and then participate
in state games.
And then you qualify in even years to participate in odd years at nationals.
And we sent 225 Oklahoma to nationals and they were in Albuquerque in 2019.
The games that you just saw pictures of.
I'm sure some place there you saw in Oklahoma.
Okay.
So they'd be done every other year.
Nationals are every other year.
Our state games are every single year.
And you would want to have games every single year too because otherwise you,
it's like anything.
You lose people if you don't do it annually.
And we pick events, we pick the events that we want to put on there.
The events.
So we could do a school bus driving.
Yeah.
Really?
Is there pickleball?
pickleball?
Oh, yeah.
The other thing is we are available to council in to help you with any.
We put together how to put on games while the parts and recreation department already know
how to do that.
That's just suggestions.
Is they want to have t-shirts?
Oh, we need to stand up for that.
Yeah.
We have to see our t-shirts.
That's great.
I know.
So I can, you know, when you get over it, get our age.
I don't care if you get a pretty stand.
Yeah.
I don't know.
So I can just place the button.
That's the same as me.
That's the same.
You know, we just had a 5K here last weekend and there was a gentleman around the 5K that was
three week short of his 9th birthday.
I remember we ran with the cane the whole time and he's from Grove so
Chuck Bullock grew up in Pitcher
Okay, okay, so what is the recreation director from Moore she put on or is in the process actually
of putting on games for the first year so
Actually, I've been the partner creation director in the war since purchased it all over a year
This was our first year of having the games in Moore so it was a development of thing and it was
fun to get the seniors to decide what they wanted to do
So we offered 10 things which included things like pickleball, tennis, table tennis, basketball
which is a hot shop contest. It's not like they get out there and are you know 515
It depends on what they want to do and some of them couldn't actually because we have older seniors
The younger one seemed to still be working and couldn't get off for the game
So we adapted and started asking them what they wanted to do
So we also went to dominoes and hearts and they liked to play some card games and peg games and things like that
So we added those to the games and they're really enjoying that
Pickable ball is growing, it's crazy and we had a fantastic pickable tournament that they just were thrilled about
But one thing I did want to say is it's backed by the Oklahoma Recreation and Part Society
which is the state society for all people in my profession and arts recreation
And we are developing that through that organization
So it's well received within the profession and we're trying to encourage that
We were doing really well until COVID came and we had a cancelled conventions and all sorts of different things
And we're just not starting to get back out. That's why there's so few locals we had about
15 at one time and then we just hadn't stopped last year because of the fire
So so you do this like one weekend
We've just actually it's been running from June and our last one is October 11th with the golf tournament
So it just we spread it out as much as possible and to find out when the seniors are more likely to have a tournament
So if they're always playing table tennis on Thursday morning we're going to have a tournament on that time
And it's really the Parks and Regration Department and volunteers
You might have a bowling center that could do it, you know, and you just work with that group
And figure out a fee that works best for the seniors so that is a lot of a month experience
So we think of that too, you know, when we have five dollar an entry fee
You know, so that everybody can get into it and we have scholarships if they need it
We don't like to even talk about fees if they can
do it. We want to encourage everybody. The main emphasis is health and fitness. We've got
to get seniors out of their homes, just sitting by themselves and not doing anything. We've
got to get them out there eating nutritionally and running. Those people that are nationals
that's not the majority of our seniors. The majority of our seniors are sitting at home and
one team of things to do. So that's why our emphasis is better health, not only mentally,
but in other places. Each city decides, like you can, they do everything in two weekends
and during the week and it's done. Oklahoma City hasn't spread out over months, so each
city does their games the way that fits them. So different events could be a different
location depending on what partners we could come up with. And you have the tribes that they're
excited about it. They're interested in partnering with each partner with you. Okay, I
would suggest them. You don't want to get any questions? Thank you. Thank you for that. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you all. Appreciate it. From the 13 local environmental action demand, demanded, led agency,
initiative petition from TechSynth and Dark Creek presentation. Martin, lively.
So thank you all for giving us some time to speak.
We are seeing a long, epic signatures on what appears to be my
first ever initiative edition, seeking a more action
importance.
Tark Creek was seen as a treasurer, by this
colon management, not any other option.
But for decades, most people in many people in this collection
say most, many people in this room have known
part of vehicles exclusively at this place,
stay away from them, not to go to.
It doesn't take care of us, and it is.
This initiative edition process, as we have gathered
signatures, has been truly remarkable.
This student has always said that people really do care.
And I think war really is a universal concern,
and that's certainly been born out.
People are taking the pen side of our hand,
and say we're in less of them.
Tark Creek deserves to be treasurer again.
And city of May, I will not bring up Tark Creek.
We indeed use that to be working on that for decades.
The city of May, I'm just going to be partnering with that for decades.
But what we can do with what each citizen who's
signing this petition is doing is building
toward that future.
I say we don't want anyone else making any worse.
This is an opportunity to say it's a commune.
No one.
We're not going to allow anybody to make it any worse.
This petition's been put forward by James Cash,
check the rocks and the John Holds, his opponents.
And they all live on Tark Creek.
I think this vote was taken over.
Is this on your property?
No.
Do you want to punch in?
Tark Creek deserves to be.
viewable, it deserves to be cleaned, it deserves to have bright, and we deserve to give ourselves the chance to pay ourselves the honor of being able to have the soft skills.
And I want to speak a little bit to this process and to some concerns that I think that some council members may have.
But I want to start, I'm, you know, former lawyer, former government instructor at any of our time.
I want to start with with with a question of why are we doing this, why do it is why why go through an initial education process.
Well, from Supreme Court in 2007 case, stated that except for the reservation except for the reservation of power of the power of initiative, the referendum, the same policy making power as best it exclusively.
This is about policy. This is about what do we, as a community, hold dear and want to make a policy.
It is unusual for all of us, none of us has been through this before, but the initial education process is designed for communities to make policy, to make statements, and to set policy for government to follow.
One concern that I think may have come, does the ordinance require the city to see anyone in everyone?
No, this ordinance creates some dooms, what may be called mandatory dooms.
Would you need to implement to defend it to enforce the ordinance?
Those are the city's dooms. The ordinance establishes rights for far greater rights than those people, how money out to have clean water.
On the city, if this ordinance asks, well, how do you do to implement it to enforce it?
You note that the ordinance does not specify how to carry out those dooms.
The ordinance does not tell you, you must do this by assuming people, or you must do this by not assuming people.
The means and the methodologies, that is for the city to be grabbed.
The city has broad discretion to have fulfilled the dooms.
This is something you see in cases repeatedly.
It is a duty to make a courthouse during her share.
This is a duty to educate children in public schools.
But when those dooms are challenged by people saying, you need to do it the right way.
Courthouse always deferred.
Because the means, what is necessary varies from circumstances to circumstances.
And...
This is new. This is different. This is not an attempt at the horde at all, to give a waterway to the residents and to say people enforce the choice.
And we will develop a system for analyzing those who violate the choice.
But that doesn't mean that lawsuits and prosecutions are the only tool we can.
They can be the tools of last resort and you folks as city councilmen and Mr. Reeves.
As the city manager, Mr. Lawrence, the attorney and Mr. Parker is the mayor.
You all have a role to play as leaders of our community in determining how do we go out for buildings.
Enforcement is about more than naming, naming and shaping.
I want a good example of that with Jane and Thomas.
They spilled it to the top group.
She didn't have it.
Did you ask me 10,000 fish done?
What did they do?
They said, oh my god, the are sorry.
And they did not contest a 10,000 dollar fine.
Why do you think that is?
One reason is they wanted to be in good standing with this community,
which cares about the part we can think.
Just saying there is a penalty.
Can have a positive influence on how people behave.
Because one thing you can say is there was no suggestion.
I'm aware of it.
The Jane and I did anything intentionally to call us that and spill.
All the implications are.
Everything that I know will be considered as that.
Still.
We're going to get it taken care of.
Now only do they pay their 10,000 dollar fine.
But they spent a million dollars to make sure it never happens.
So that those pipes, the first, the fuel, the place, done better.
Because there was a consequence.
And part of that consequence is the public perception and the public statement that we want to protect this group.
The problem is there's always going to be a combat at that level somewhere.
Someone who really doesn't want to do the right thing.
It's important we are caretakers within the group.
It's important that we utilize our water to their units to reach out to folks.
So you don't just have to file a lawsuit.
You don't just have to cross-use someone in municipal criminal court.
You can use public education in public education.
As you develop the rules, the standards,
what does a clean target mean, what is actionable
as a potential prosecution in what is not.
You can reach out to the public,
into key business leaders in the community who have demonstrated
to think care about, chart-free, any other?
Jane, out.
You can involve those folks if you so choose.
Help build public consensus and support
for those who are wrong, you can't do it.
Might possibly one day, cause it more.
Make sure everybody understands.
Here's what we're looking at.
And once they're developed,
you can public outreach and say,
this is what we expect from our community,
that goes a long way to prevent a violation,
because a long way to prevent having to sue anyone.
But if something does happen,
there are tools, or if that you have some existing powers,
hardest community concern.
You can establish boards.
You can establish trustee counsels.
There are various tools in your toolkit already.
And there are people in this community of high-end low status,
of high-end and low income,
who care about this career.
And who I believe,
if the city said we want to establish a community board
to care and be a voice for our free in a conjunction with the decisions
of city government,
I think there are people with sign-up.
You can create that board if you so desire.
I'm not saying you should it.
But you can.
There are alternatives in ways to build the community support,
so that you don't have to become adversarial.
You can also work with the tribes who are testing,
and targeting people.
You can work with BQ and EPA from a data and sign-up,
as a perspective.
You can work with U.S. G.S.
to get screened into data.
And all you're doing is for flooding and other things like that.
These are all tools that we have.
The enforcement comes necessary.
You don't have to jump straight through all things.
You can send out informal enforcement matters.
You can get up high-finding investigations.
There's something worthy of investigation
that may or may not rise from the public policy.
You can send out notices by a mission.
There are all sorts of informal mechanisms
to address and lose all that.
Without having to become adversarial confrontation,
DQ is a great example of that.
They, that is exactly what they did.
In the case of the J&P,
so they did, ultimately, send out a notice of violation.
They did.
And you see this throughout agencies responsible for enforcement.
You see informal education, right?
Notice this in five relations.
There are lots of ways to resolve incidents of interference
with corporate choice and future.
But I'm just happy.
So, frankly, it shouldn't be a lot of them.
Shouldn't be the same to that point.
Walk into any criminal court.
90 percent of the case that's 93 percent.
And on the jurisdiction.
They're not resolved with trials.
They're resolved with unions.
They're resolved.
My folks stay okay.
Let's just get this done.
We have lots of options.
We want to close out, by returning to a lawyer's scope.
The home constitution tries to all political powers
and guaranteeing the people.
You are our leaders.
You are this communities.
We're here.
We want to protect our group.
We want to go beyond relying on the EU.
We want to do a thing.
Namely, to put a stake in the ground.
And to say, we will not let our group get any worse.
It may take decades to get to our group fully clean.
We can't speed that up.
You can't speed that up.
Not significant.
Now, unless you get really, really lucky.
And we'll somehow divide into administrations.
As let's put another $300,000,000 in Star Creek.
That would be great.
We should do that.
But we all be thrilled.
But what we can't be honest with you is to say that if someone makes it worse,
I'm dumping into Star Creek, preventing Dark Creek from flourishing,
and existing and flowing as she should,
then we will hold that person accountable.
Now, let's be honest.
The accountability here is mostly politics.
It's mostly saying, what this happened, and you need to own up to it.
$750.
We're asking if things back from the fight for the under-disorders is not huge.
Now, for the most likely offenders.
What we're talking about here is making a statement of policies.
And what we, the community, feel we need to protect Dark Creek,
which should, again, be a treasure.
Should, again, can we hope, join us, taking us one step closer?
We hope that we will pass this ordinance because community support at the leader.
of level is important. It matters. You may recall last time when you're here as Jim spoke to you about some boys who were swimming in Parkory.
That's them. Those are those boys. That was a month ago. That's Parkory.
Note two things. One, it's tragedy that we have to be worried about that one thing.
Number two, that part is really gorgeous. It wouldn't have been nice if that were safe.
We need to do everything we can to protect Parkory.
And I've been to several city councils in Alaska.
I hear each time important conversation about it.
If you're wondering, is this going to hurt economic development for my animal?
To say we're going to punish people who pull in Parkory.
Is this going to slow down what we can do is community about this?
What's the biggest impediment to getting a big thriving successful business to moving their families to this community?
Is having a poison creep that's carrying left through our community?
Now we can't change that if you can't change that.
But imagine if we could say to every business wanting to maybe maybe move 40 families, 50 families, 600 families to this community.
But worried about the state of that, we can imagine if we can say to that, it isn't clean yet.
But we have no business making a crime for anybody with all due respect.
You included business perspective, this is an unexpected business woman.
If anybody makes it worse, we're going to hold you accountable.
If you want to draw business, you want to draw sustainable business.
Business is not only the creep worse, we've got it if you want to draw it.
And I'm really, really, I feel very strongly about this.
I mean, my great-grandfather moved to Pitcher in 1917,
and along with our senior's London company, because of the mines.
Mine's cause of this.
We can't accept it.
I really hope that you folks will join us.
Join the people who are signing and saying, no one.
No one. No one can do it.
If you do it, shame on you.
I don't think that's too much as a city that wants to grow and so I appreciate your time.
I've well given questions and as Jim is here, I think she breaks the lobby to do this presentation.
But both of us, either of us would be happy in certain questions you've had.
It concerns about the ordinance saying in your one great battle.
We are here.
Mr. Lively, if I may, I do have one question.
Something that I was just trying to identify and as a city manager, you can imagine I'm the guy that worries a lot about the dollars and cents.
Yes, of course.
So any time that we talk about a ordinance that identifies an obligation on the city,
I got to make sure I fully understand it because I want to understand those obligations.
And one of the things that I was interested in is between a couple of the versions that you all had executed, I guess, or had shared.
Originally as far as the responsibility of the city, the language read that it was the city would do what was reasonable and necessary.
And may consider budgetary and fiscal consequences as we execute this ordinance.
But in a more recent version, it was changed that the city shall take all necessary actions to defend.
Meaning we have no choice for financial responsibilities or budget concerns we just have to.
And that was what I wanted to ask. Why did you go that direction with it and take away the vision?
There are a couple of friends there.
That's a good question. I appreciate your ask.
Sure.
There are a couple of friends.
One piece is question.
What you did not ask.
What is the actual significance of the change?
Number one, I want to speak to that.
As I have been looking at some cases, and looking at how many trade duties are structured, there is a key distinction between what is the duty and what is the means of executing the right.
The difference between those two phrases is sound significant.
I don't know.
I don't think it really hits, and I'll tell you why.
When I look at examples that I've found
of mandatory duties, writing, providing educational
children's good example, the other one called
institution provides that, and I'm not going to get
these works exactly right, but the, but I look at it
just this morning, so it's fresh in my mind,
that the state shall provide an education to students.
There's no qualifiers, there's no nothing.
And yet, in case after case,
arguing over whether the state can do
XYZ version XYZ means implementing that
duty to write.
The course has said, the means are not specified.
The duty is the duty to educate.
The methodology, the means, the priorities,
that's all politics.
That's all a question of priorities,
and the determinations that the Department of Education
has the experts within government on educating students.
They can make those decisions,
and they can balance those priorities.
And they're going to give in by the course of law
that we're going to give in a great deal of discretion.
That is to say, as someone says,
I don't like the way you did that.
That is a secondary education.
Absent very, very good calls.
Show.
The course are going to set the secondary education
as the experts, how to educate children, how to allocate
scarce resources throughout the state, across schools,
and school districts.
All right, we will generally speaking defer to the expertise
of the secondary education as to how that duty is carried out.
Now, we're at the secondary education to say,
no, we're just shutting down all the schools outside
to also know what was it.
That's totally different,
because they're the second few areas
to advocate for duty entirely.
So number one, on balance,
I don't think that it's as significant
in a difference as it appears.
Number two, why make the change?
Because it's a statement of principle.
This is intended to reflect
well, frankly, I mean, to be honest,
when there was an initial graph,
there was some discussion about what was permissible
and what was not so bad.
with the city through Mr. War and about that, and to be honest, we wanted to see people look a little bit of a top or state, and you use some top or language, right?
But as I have read the cases, and I'll be very candid with you, Mr. Reeves. This has been since we made that change.
As I have read the cases, I've been, as an activist, so let this make, honestly, what I've found, the degree of death runs given, is significant.
I think the city has a great deal of life, the language is strong, yes. But think about it this way.
It's also strong language that we can stand behind collectively as state of principle value and policy.
How you implement that you are at the experts in how to run the city government, and I think that you folks are going to have a task.
Whether this is voted for by the city council or whether it is voted for in the ballot box, there will be a challenge, no doubt, right?
But look at all the team members to help and to help identify options, right?
Thankfully, we don't have skills in tomorrow for every day, thankfully, there will be time to figure out how to do this.
But that how is within your discretion. That language, to be blunt, was circumstances in the first question, as I went back out of the panel.
It was in, it was circumstances, this makes it stronger, singular principle, but as I read it, you still would have a fair amount of discretion now.
Do not take my word for this, and Mr. Warren, I would be happy to show you the cases that I found.
But I think that the city would have my attitude, right? What cannot be ignored is the do need to implement to defend it to enforce.
These things would have to be done. It would have to be implemented, it would have to be defended, or a challenge, and it would have to be enforced, or someone to violate it, right?
Those things may not be ignored. They are duties created by this ordinance, yes?
If someone actually violates it, right? Why would we not want to implement it? Why would we not want to adopt an ordinance that says we will not let anyone make target works?
It's a investment in our future.
It's the best of all those kids playing in a dark, great game of games, who want to, and frankly, places that are already glued and to get glued or I look at my internet.
I've lived places, I've been from here, back in the world here, but I've moved around and I've lived other places.
The degree of challenge that this community basis is shocking, the conscience.
And I am amazed that we have not suffered more repeat ongoing new environmental harm.
We are a magnet for people to just come and feel like they've done more.
Yeah, there's a lot of work to do on your right.
But I think you have the discretion to take all these things into account here.
So if I may, one other question, I just want to make sure that I'm understanding, because this is pretty new.
But to all of us, clearly, in everybody I think obviously could agree, clean water is extremely important.
Most of us grew up here in my, and have experienced tar creek before it turned orange before it polluted and stained our houses and killed our fish and turtles.
Times in which we grew up in which we could actually safely get in the water.
So we thought.
But earlier you were talking about the Jane and Farms.
And when they polluted the creek accidentally, you say it was EPA.
DQ, find them $10,000.
So in the future, would that still occur in that same manner?
And so DQ would still have a responsibility to protect and defend tar creek.
So other than the $10,000 they were finding than we had come along and just hit them with a $750 final top of that.
Well that would be how's that said?
That would be up to the city.
Right.
So for example.
And this goes back to that language you asked about right.
Right.
What is necessary?
Now I would say as to the language very briefly.
This serene and possible are two very different words.
That's something as possible to not make it necessary.
What is necessary depends on what's best for the creek for the community.
And even for the widely.
So different circumstances may call for different types of responses.
Let's take Jane and Farms.
Let's say that that happened again.
The same facts.
DQ comes in.
Right.
It's real.
for it to decrease.
City and DQ both find that there is violation of their relevant statutory and ordinance for
these.
DQs forward, they say we're going to have to have a 10 has no time.
City of Miami, right, may choose to do differently if they so desire.
They could say we're going to issue a letter of referment if that were authorized by procedures,
right?
It is a disinstance, you know, we note that Janet Farms has always been at the
obscure decree and that all the evidence is that this was an accidental discharge, not
an intentional discharge.
We note that they are complied with DQ, right?
And we find them in violation, but we are simply issuing a letter of referment in a little
final.
Right?
Or if you felt, or if Mr. Lorang is the city attorney, that was more serious despite DQ's
significant, but nonetheless informal resolution to the matter.
Mr. Lorang may say, you know what, we need to take this in to this for, or I want this on the
record as violation.
And they neither admit their bill or they can go to trial, as assistant, right?
But we're going to take this through that process, because I feel that the community deserves
the creep deserves a more significant penalty, and this is what we can do if we're going to do
that.
But the city would have choice.
This prosecutorial discretion, right?
I'm a cyclist.
I write these streets all the time.
Do my best to follow the rules of road, why, like every other vehicle on the road?
I see cyclists all the time, who ride on the sidewalks, who ride against traffic, who
you ride and have a helmet, who legally.
Do I see them get pulled over, stopped, inside it?
No.
Why?
Because police officers make the decision, it's not worth enforcing, right?
Now, I wouldn't say that those two things are equal, including property disperse by police
public has or not just a hazard to yourself.
But nonetheless, there is always discretion.
There's always discretion.
What would the county, if it all, what would their role be in this?
So since Tarkree obviously goes beyond the city limits of Miami, would the county have a role
in this at all?
Well, so there are two pieces to that.
And the first, which I don't think you quite are asking out, but I'm going to address it very
legally and because it's important, because the speed spec questioner can be now.
Give me a question.
Some were found polluting in the talk room.
The city could go straight into county court district court,
as public nuisance.
This ordinance would create a nuisance by operation of law.
Once that exists, there are existing ordinances
that already allow the city to take any public nuisance
to find my ordinance directly into district court.
So in terms of things that float downstream,
the city of Miami, through parkry,
that create public nuisance here,
the district court is able to deal with that.
And there's already an infrastructure in place for that.
Now in terms of the county as a governmental entity
on the enforcement side, that is,
I'm assuming you're thinking on the enforcement side.
Yes, that's right.
That is an interesting question.
I mean, I don't think that the county can enforce a municipal ordinance
number one.
Number two, there's no initiative petition process
at the county level in Oklahoma to the best of my knowledge.
The county could possibly take up,
and I believe they could,
take up a version of this ordinance that will operate at the county level.
Counties do have authority to protect public health and welfare.
And to our creek, as you've seen,
we still have children swimming in tarpreets.
So tarpreets is a factor of four toxins.
Hoses of public health threat, potentially, if it is dumped into.
And so were they to do that?
I believe yes, they could play a role in enforcement.
This floor, and you may have some insights into this.
I'm not seeing a county enforcement angle
in the way that I think you're asking this for weeks.
I think that they would have a role in any public nuisance proceeding,
brought in district court, and we're the district court.
This actually may be more instructive.
We're the district court to find a nuisance,
upon the city, bringing a nuisance action under this ordinance.
Do you have a violation?
Some of them don't.
You go into district court.
You say, if we have a public nuisance in Atlanta,
this is what happened at violates this ordinance, protecting tarpreet.
The district court rules in your favor.
They say, a statement action is appropriate.
They are under this actually.
People leave a herd outside the city limits of Atlanta.
Then at that point, the district court could issue an order of,
presumably, for the sheriff's office, right, to move forward
with an abation action, somewhere north of the United States.
So they could help with enforcement if it's a public nuisance.
I was a criminal misdemeanor.
I don't think they could.
because that's all just in the city you might have on me this before.
And that's part of the beauty of this audience.
Right?
It gives you two sets of tools.
One you sort of have already.
But what it does is it defines this as a public nuisance.
It gives you all the, well, of public nuisance tools that already exist
at the city end of the county level.
And two gives you the added tool of a public nuisance.
And what hopefully will be those written cases for that's appropriate.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, I think so.
Okay.
Yeah.
Sorry.
On the expert at walking answers to the simple questions.
I apologize.
So I got a question going back to your scenario.
Where you said the gin and farm set of spill.
DQ comes in 5 and 10,000.
We can be in 5 and 750.
Through all that talk.
We never said anything about cleaning that up.
What?
Where's the cleanup part coming in that?
Okay.
Good question.
So DQ, there are two pieces to that.
DQ side and the city frame of side.
DQ has authorities and its regulations to mandate cleanup efforts as part of the course
of national leave.
So they can't handle part of it.
Right.
Now, as to the city of my own side.
At 750 dollars or whatever the fine is, the baby assessed if less than 750.
Um, the women's specifies that it shall be used only to clean up a talk freak.
And again, the city will have some discretion about how to manage that because I can infercene two scenarios.
One scenario.
The actual cost of cleaning up is much much more than 750 dollars.
Right.
And another scenario where and we'll use this as a touch.
Let's say that the DQ orders them to clean up their mess.
Right.
And on the DQ side, they did.
Well, then that 750 dollars.
I would suggest the city could set up.
A restoration for a talk freak.
And they would have to set that money aside to clean up talk freak.
Right.
Can't be used for anything else under your arms.
So the city of Miami, hopefully this won't happen often.
I think the harder the city is when there is a DQ action.
Why you've got to spill.
And the DQ for whatever reason says,
We're not going to do it.
We're going to do it.
Or they fail in their effort.
Right.
It's a closed call.
What's actually responsible for this damage.
Then you have a much tougher situation, who's going to, you know,
the city of Miami is the only enforcer that is successful, and this is a pretty
und... I want to say, this is a very un-white-free factually unlikely height of that point,
is unlikely that this will actually happen. But if it did, then I think the news
and tools would come into play more and usefully than the clinical tools.
Yes, you can order a restitution, be paid, and if you're bound with equals of clean up.
That's one quick example. The order is specified, the target is legal victim,
for any violations. Like any other legal victim, she would be entitled to
restitution for damages, whatever damages, the cost of cleaning up the damage
caused by this film. And so those could be ordered, right? And then that money also
is held back if it's not all needed to actually clean up this damage. Because
the creeks can sometimes heal themselves a little bit, time can heal a little bit. But nonetheless,
that money must be saved to protect our creek to restore our creek.
So, let's say they have a spill. Yep. And by the time it's noticed and everything's
talked about, it's to the dam. Yep. Now, we've got to clean that up and seek restitution.
No. No. That would be outside of the jurisdiction of court in the US at the scope of yours.
We can protect our creek from the dam. It's not in all jurisdiction.
Okay, would you have a clamp to spill, right?
We have to clean up. Let me check a language of the ordinance,
is that he helps matter here. Okay. So, if we look at D3 in the text of the ordinance,
I'll take some of these restitution under a subsection to the D3 to the restitution shall be
measured or dealt with D1. For purposes of the ordinance, the creek has been equated and legal rights
which may be violated. So, he is informed. So, he shall be, if they've done restitution shall be measured
by the cost of fully restoring the creek to its previously existing state for the violations.
Because the creek is heavily impaired by the institution shall not be measured by restoration
through to a natural temporary state. So, on support of restitution shall be paid to the city,
my amateur business, exclusively for the full and complete restoration of the creek
has affected by the violation. Now, we do take a broad definition of chart pre-inclusive ecosystem,
a particular ecosystem, which includes tributaries in the chart for the watershed.
So, there may be an instance where there is damage within the watershed.
The city is going to be limited in where a natural extent that you are correct. Why?
But again, this is where the partnership is coming to play. I want to say, because I think you raised really good.
white, we are part of it.
What we are doing here is different.
It's an entirely different approach
to protecting the environment.
It's one based on the whites of tarpreying
the whites of the people.
The book hasn't been written on how to do this.
And this is one of those areas where, yeah,
we're going to have to kind of figure it out.
I don't have the perfect answer for you to do something
outside of the watershed.
But what I can say is, from everything that I know,
the city of Mayala has very good relationships
with upstream and downstream communities in general.
If there is damage elsewhere in the tarpreying watershed,
I am very confident that the city will work
with the downstream or upstream partners
in the case may be jurisdictions.
And when that time comes, everyone's going
to act in good faith to find the answer.
I don't have that answer to that precise question.
But this kind of, we all share this damage from my view.
We all share the consequences of it.
We use the metals already in all of our waterways.
We all have statements.
Now, I think that an answer can be found
to that more into a curve.
I don't know what that is.
Just talking through it.
I don't know if I have the answer or not a question.
But it strikes me as a question that when you know
the facts in the context around it, which it occurred,
who was the guilty party, how did it get downstream?
How much are we talking about, right?
That's another thing.
The amount of damage can vary widely here.
If we're not about catastrophic passive damage,
and the ecosystem, that is a very different analytical
ballpark than we've got 500 damage.
They're both the tragedy.
But they are completely different in scope and the way they're going to be.
So, what has contained in a dark creek?
We have numerous contaminants to be required.
We have my legs, heavy metals, lead, zinc, arsenic,
right from the top of the creek.
Stop right there for just saying, how you say that?
So, every time we get a hard rain, that water comes out of the chat
piles on the pitcher and it's orange, it's coming down,
you know, working more contaminants.
What do we do about that?
Well, so, there what you have is the situation where the question would be.
is the most common point of comparison in the world,
wall would be toward transverse negligence to the breach of duty.
You have to get negligence.
Is there a duty load, did someone breach the duty,
and is there a causation between the breach of the duty
in the harm that was suffered?
Right? In this case, that would be clearly way outside
those realms, those realms. Right?
You cannot, I think, in good conscience, make an argument
that some legal entity caused
that is currently in existence today caused
that harm. Right?
That harm exists because of pre-existing conditions.
By pre-existing, I mean, before and before
the ordinance was in that case.
So is that in the ordinance?
No. It is not.
It's a basic principle. It's just legal interpretation
and there are rules of a political statutenant structure
when you interpret statutes.
There are rules, of course, to use.
To interpret them, this is in similar ways.
There are also court cases saying,
what rules to follow when you have certain sort of structural
question from the law that come on,
such as how do you determine duty and causation?
Right?
That's the whole case books on court law
that address those questions of what are the answers.
But I would guess, and if you want to try to ignore,
I wonder those facts, if all you have is
all my damage, it rains, water comes up
and it flows into the creek, carrying more contaminants
from underground.
It doesn't seem to mean, there's any breach of duty there.
By an party who can be killed before the court, right?
You could make an argument, I suppose,
that has an environmentalist.
I would love it if someone did.
If you could find the person, right?
Who we could point out, you are responsible for that morhole, right?
Or for that, that, you know, but again, we're dealing with
the force in our nature.
And so, common sense doesn't lead the room,
and I think this would be my base in the room.
There's common sense doesn't lead the room,
because you're bringing lawyers into it.
There's still that basic sort of came back
to find the person who's legally responsible.
Now, you know, there may be scenarios
where failure all over regulations related to the
side might be an issue, okay?
There might be instances where there are regulations
that go right and conduct and questions of...
of run-off from work sites, if someone violates those duties, those rules and allows
to talk to run-off from the work site where they're handling chat.
Well, yeah, maybe that's a question, right?
And again, we know the contractors, we know the folks who are doing that work out there, we
build the relationships.
This is an opportunity for everybody to do better.
Okay, this is not a game of gacha, this is not a game of gacha, we're also going to
be got this new rule, and now gacha, gacha, is going to take time to develop the means
of implementing this.
This is not nor this, you can just drop on the books and everybody knows what to do with
that.
I'm sure this remains here, probably thinking, I don't want to have that response really
to do it right then and there.
It's going to take some time to implement it, but the great thing is everybody knows the
torpedoes can tamade already, everybody knows that she's damaged, everybody wants to do the
right thing, right, everybody involved, the tribes do, the agencies do, the city governments do,
you have all the partners you need to avoid to get, we're making a living retreat to this,
to give every person who might contaminate our creek as a predictable potential pilot of
this ordinance, right?
There is ample opportunity, ample food will, and the animals here to get everybody knowing what's
coming, right, to build an understanding of it.
This is what this ordinance is going to mean as we implement it, okay?
You can do informal methods of resolving any problems that occur, you do not simply have to
find a lawsuit, but if you call across somebody who's so in-premises, who says, no, I'm not
going to take these steps to protect our creek, no, I'm not going to stop this one, no, I'm
not going to repair my pipes and prevent another spill like that, no, I don't want to,
because I just don't want to, look, anybody deserves to be sued, isn't it that person who
then actually balloons start breathing, I mean, isn't that one of the rare instances where
it would actually be appropriate to say, you know what, okay, you know, we've created all these
ways to work it out, we've been talking with you, we've brought all those to your attention,
right?
We sent you a letter saying, look, we believe that you're in violation of this rule from DQ or this rule from EPA.
And we believe this is causing damage to the industry.
We believe that violins are organs, come meet with us, and let's work it out.
Let's fix it, and they say, no.
And no.
Is that really someone who deserves the chance to just, well,
they're a nice person.
We want to be a good man.
We do want to be good in neighbors.
But when you're being a good neighbor,
and those efforts aren't specifically,
and are free, and those kids,
may be the ones to pay the price.
And our community may be in price,
because if the damage is really bad, my God.
And yeah, maybe we should have seen that person.
And maybe we should stand up and say we're proud to have seen that,
but unfortunately, we wish we never had it.
But I don't think we should have come to that very often,
because most people are working with in this county,
want to do the right thing.
But we need this consequence there.
So you, the city council, the city of Miami, or generally,
have a tool that you can use proactively.
Right now, right now, let's take that case.
So you think they're not managing their blood off,
and they're not preparing their pipes.
You call up to EQ, you report it.
That's great.
Now, we're dependent on the kindness of strangers.
We hope they do the right thing.
We want you to be able to do the right thing in addition.
Just say, yeah, we're going to report you to EQ.
But we're also going to do our part,
and we as a community are going to protect ourselves,
as much as we can.
And this gives you a little tool.
Get everybody the chance to be a better student.
That person.
You may have any more questions.
All right.
Thank you.
If you have any questions, more than anyone else has any.
Well, 14.
Improve my public school's traffic control plan recommendations.
Chief, high tower.
Well, I was going to school here.
The high school and the little school meeting combine.
They want to add a stop.
at the high school. Currently, they're getting turned central. The southbound, at the stop sign
that we have no control at all. So the school is asked to be put in a four-way intersection
of four-way stop sign type intersection. And we have some pictures here. This will be the
intersection here. You have the returner. There's new road, there's a round of school.
Buses for drop-off and high school are coming out to the intersection.
So you can have a lot more of a four-way traffic there. We're doubling the number of students
at the high school in a quiet house. So this is going to be interesting to see how
traffic works out there. I believe in this again, it's the intersection right here we're
just making it a four-way. Elven Central, be this intersection here. It's going to be
a next concern. And I don't know how to fix that right now. We're going to watch that
to the start of school. But we do want to go and add these now. I work a four-way
place there temporarily. And so the council will make the permit
correction. Just to give people a use of school coming out to be a totally new situation.
There is going to be significant amount of traffic that intersection. And we come up with
several conversations on doing a traffic plane. And there's just one road in and one road
out. It's not ideal for the amount of people around there. You see that added that the road
around and the new footprint of the school. So in that one, they just want to add a
stop, stop, stop, stop, stop. The other road, I don't know if I took a picture of it by the middle school,
on the E3, the wrong. I mean, it's currently one-way street. It's that middle school traffic
and the vehicles, which are going to be up our elementary. We want to change that back to a two-way
street to get rid of the one-way, come around. And it's just going to make that a
little easier to get back to the nickels up our elementary. Well, the E-side of the junior high?
Yes. The junior high is not being used. It's just the boys and girls club.
They're trying to back in the back at the up our elementary, and they're supposed to all
down. So they want to be able to get back there a little easier and make that a two-way road.
We change that three or four years ago when it, whatever it was, to make it one
way to, with the bus there and all the parents pick up a bit of one way to go
into there. So they want to get back to two.
It would be right right through here and just change that back to it to the road.
I know that stop signs very needed there at the high school, just from doing the work right there.
Yeah.
People still aren't stopping, but when you put the middle right there, they're bad.
And we want to get that up.
Some of the council will be going to make that a hermd of thing or a recommendation.
We want to start that and give people just aware of it.
We didn't want that to go up right before.
So we didn't put a temporary one there.
Hoping that it would start to get people's attention.
We have not started working that day right now.
We just hope to get people's attention.
Give them a little bit of a report.
Let them know that they're going to be assigned there.
That's going to be a significant amount of traffic coming through there.
I don't know if they're busslingered out.
Or people get around there.
Parents help them.
No school.
The medical drop off.
And for an answer, it's going to be back over here.
So parents are going to come around and then back out.
So they'll be going to the south or through here.
High schools come here and out.
And then there's normal traffic.
And the planning is just to watch out for the board.
Let's see how it does.
And the redevite way.
I wrote it down.
It's going to be an issue.
I'm a central.
Even with this top line.
Okay.
Get already back up.
Do there.
The morning south.
I'm trying to turn in.
It's a problem.
I think that left me heard.
And we're double-stoot.
It's going to be back up.
We've looked for other ideas.
We're talking about doing one way.
Straight all the way through and out.
Then again.
I was a little traffic.
And then trail far there.
We've looked a lot of different things.
And they're just not.
Right now.
I'll make a motion.
We could have stopped on there.
I'll second.
Is that both the one line now?
Yes.
Okay.
The only thing I suggest is that that four-way stop.
It has the white paint on the ground.
Instead of just no stops.
I'm maybe the flashing ones.
That's all I was thinking of.
The flashing ones.
Just to have the light.
Have it painted on the ground.
Right.
Crosswalk.
We're going to stop.
Right.
Paint on the ground.
Yeah.
It's got to be real visible.
Can you put?
Do you have regular stops on?
You can put up till you get the flashing ones?
I will make a motion to put up the stop signs.
I have changed the one way traffic to two way traffic.
I'll say.
Dougal.
Hi.
Parker.
Thank you, so Ben, what are I doing there man, should you be anything and then jump back six o'clock
We're past six so you have a good do it you're doing it now. Why you can finish all we're doing here
We're going in a jacket, so
So do I need to jump over do it and then come back. Yes, so I just have a pause in that meeting here
What we need to continue this meeting to be reconvening after the NSC and the she way
Okay, we need the same ring all right, then he said that or second enough
That is your motion. I'll adopt that as well. Motion. So in the second or first. I'll
I'll strike in it
What call the or the right your me the MSUA or on the 23rd 2021
Education by
Thank you for the importance of this city.
I thank you for this great country-lit win.
Yeah, that's true.
God, the decisions of our leaders of this country
and people in Afghanistan.
Most of all, God, I thank you for your sudden use, Christ.
It's in his name on Friday.
Thank you.
I quite believe it's to the five of the United States
of America, to the Republic for which it stands.
One nation, one nation, one nation, and one nation.
It's a little bit of a need for justice for all.
Four public input or personal, I was going to go to personal parenthesis.
And then five considered gender staff recommends we approve out of six in seven.
I'll make the motion approve.
Second.
Parker.
Hi.
Mr. Fierce.
Hey.
Final project.
Close out change.
We're table number nine.
Approved.
JRDA legal claims boaries. So this is a recent invoice for our MSUA legal fees, which is
a great example of why I get nervous when we talk about legal fees. We have an invoice
for 93,530 dollars for Davis Wright to Maine in Goodall Stratten regarding the Pints
Colored Realizing Thing and the Rule Curve Change. These are per the contract we have
for legal expenses.
Having questions on those claims about the answer of my name, for Ben, one, two, the question
of the long thing by?
I'm sorry, something about a contract.
Well, specifically just let you all know that these invoices are per and existing contract
that we have with the attorneys for executing these services. So any failure to pay these
invoices would leave us in breach of contract.
From breach of contract.
What does that mean, though?
We had entered into a contract with these individuals to form these services regarding the
Pinscolidium, Relicensing.
They executed on that contract and filed briefings on our behalf in District Court.
And now that they perform those services, they've submitted an invoice for us to pay for those services.
So, you know what they entered into that contract with your boy?
And we were four more times before every one of our time.
It's what a lady's been.
Before your time.
Is that a contract we can review or anything?
Look at her.
I would imagine it's a pretty review.
Since that contract was for a particular lawsuit, it was for the processes relating to the
licensing, which is not going to happen.
The time of all it takes.
And for, well, incorporated in that is the appeal of the first decision, which that's what
almost always is about.
Now, that's being done in the Circuit Court.
On the Circuit Court.
The Circuit Court.
And that is a different world.
I do not know that process.
But it's my best guess that that.
And I've looked at.
I haven't fully read any of those two briefs that they come.
It's my best guess that that is the last thing that they will be doing on that.
Except for the oral arguments, which may or may not happen, that's a determination
to be made by the Court.
Nobody has any decision deciding that you're on that other than the Court itself.
That made sense.
It could make sense.
It's a deal of not taste good.
The Green High Court.
I understand.
Motion to approve.
I'll second.
Davis.
Hi.
He's definitely.
Dockle?
Aye.
Sunder?
Nay.
Park it.
Aye.
Tim, staff reports.
11.
Trustee, community, announcements.
12, adjournment.
Motion.
Sunder?
Aye.
Motion?
Reconvening?
City Council.
Sunder?
Sorry.
Okay.
15.
Other new businesses may have risen since the posting of this agenda.
16.
Staff reports.
17.
Mayor.
City Council, community announcements.
18.
City Mallory Communications.
You know I don't have anything extensive update.
You all on tonight.
Other than I did want to give you a brief.
I count.
At one of our previous meetings, Josh Fleming can brought up and did a report on rates and rate setting.
And I just wanted it to be true along that Josh and I spent a significant amount of time reviewing this recently here at the City Hall.
And kind of going through all the different nuances of this.
Yeah, it was a very good discussion as they normally are and I sincerely appreciate his time and effort that he puts into it.
And one of the things that I had encouraged Josh was that we certainly focus on any ordinances that we look at in the future regarding rates.
That we have someone like Josh from a citizens perspective.
Review that language and make sure that it's comprehensible and understandable from from anyone that any of our citizens that have to to read an ordinance and understand how we calculate a rate and how those rates would be able to build.
I think it's extremely important that it would be done in a manner that is understandable by everyone.
I simply wanted to bring that up and for you all to hear and certainly Josh would be a great candidate for reviewing that going forward.
I appreciate his involvement.
All right, number 19, this meeting will now be continued for the Calce Chamber to
reconvene the staff room for the purpose of executive session.